I'm going to do the traditional preliminaries tomorrow and then if you
want to record it, you can put your phone up here or something tomorrow.
And then you can use it for a few days until you get used to it.
And this is the, my plan is it's the last time I'm going to do the lion's dance in Guadalajara
this week.
And then we do something new next time.
This is kind of the last review and then you have to add it to your tool kit.
Okay?
And teach it to other people.
Then it's time to go to a new one.
Okay, so here we go.
Hands can be any way you want.
There's a big problem with meditation.
It's everyone's eyes are closed.
So it doesn't matter how close your eyes are.
It doesn't matter how cool you look.
Nobody's looking.
I hope.
So just be comfortable.
Sometimes I feel more comfortable like this.
Sometimes my hand will fall asleep, so I go halfway between.
If it's cold,
I will do left hand, right hand.
Then your arms are touching your body.
And you will feel warmer.
So in my three-year retreat, we didn't have any electricity.
Some days very cold.
Some days snowing.
It snowed the first day.
And you do this way definitely.
So up to you.
Meditation is a very personal thing.
And you just do what's comfortable for you.
If karma is correct,
it doesn't matter how you sit.
I have a friend in the monastery.
He always meditates laying down.
And everyone said he's crazy.
Then one night we had a debate competition
with the other monastery.
And he was sitting down for our side.
We called Dam Cha Shak.
He was the defender.
And he was representing our monastery.
And he started to do what Hasso did.
To the other monastery's debater.
The other monastery was Tashi Humbo.
This is the Panchen Lama's monastery.
And he really destroyed the other side.
And we were all shocked because he always meditated laying down.
And when he studies he always has rock and roll music in his ears,
illegally, in the monastery.
And he beat all those guys.
Then the abbot got upset.
Tashi Hlunpo abbot.
And he's the greatest tantric master, maybe in South India.
He's Geshe Thubten Rinchen's teacher.
Then he came up, attacked our guy.
It's like the football coach running to the football.
He came and attacked him.
It's like when the football coach goes and starts playing.
And he beat him.
Then the old abbot, he took off his hat.
So it's a proof you can meditate laying down.
It doesn't really matter.
What matters is you have seed for good meditation.
The seed for good meditation is one week before you plan to meditate,
be very considerate of other people's feelings.
Like never say anything which upsets other people's feelings.
Be very careful what you say to other people.
Then you are making their mind peaceful.
Then every time you do that, you are planting seeds to have a peaceful meditation.
So that's the real secret to meditation.
It's not your hands.
Like the pen, your meditation is coming from your seeds.
All right, here we go. You ready?
So any way you want. Lay down is fine.
But I don't allow.
Okay, here we go.
Then most people, when they concentrate,
and me also,
their face gets very tight.
Like I saw a video of me playing sitar and I looked very angry.
Because my mind was like,
wow, my mind is focusing.
So now try to relax your face.
Smile.
When I was in Paris last month,
we went to see Mona Lisa.
Her smile is perfect for meditation.
Okay, small smile.
Try not to wrinkle your forehead.
And relax your eyelids.
And relax your fingers.
It's very good if you can pull in your stomach a little bit.
And keep it in just a little bit.
Okay, which is much easier if you don't overeat all day.
If you know about curving your tailbone in,
that's very good also.
And when you start to meditate,
try not to tighten your face.
You can move your shoulder blades in the back closer to each other
so your chest comes out a little bit.
And that's easier to do if you move your hands back up your leg a little bit.
And then come to your breath.
Watch your breath.
And in the lion's dance,
we go directly to some noise in the room.
So it could be the noise of your refrigerator in your house.
It could be the noise of the air conditioner in this room.
If you live in Guadalajara or Mexico,
and the traffic noise is very helpful.
The traffic is very good.
So usually those noises are obstacles.
But in the lion's dance,
we use them
to start the meditation.
So let's put our mind on the air conditioner noise.
Can you feel it?
Just take a few breaths.
As you're moving away from the air,
take a few breaths.
And as you're leaving your body,
And let your mind return to your world.
Let all of you feel it.
Okay?
Now let's go a little bit quieter.
If you're by yourself in your apartment and if it's very early in the morning,
you can start to listen to your heartbeat in your ears.
If it's later in the morning like now,
you can just go to the feeling of your heart beating in your chest.
So let's get more quiet and go to the heartbeat in your chest.
Yeah.
.
Thank you.
Now let's go more quiet.
Let's go inside our heart.
So, put your mind inside your heart.
It's not wet and messy, okay?
No, it's wet.
Make it a nice
beautiful little room.
A very sweet
meditation space.
But the walls of the apartment
are your heart.
And it's feeding.
It's feeding.
Okay.
All right.
Let's go.
Thank you.
Now let's go deeper.
Imagine your inside of your heart is like a nice penthouse apartment on a tall building.
And it has an inner room, which is even more quiet.
So go to the inner room inside the heart.
The walls are still beating, but it seems far away.
You don't hear it much.
Now imagine next to you is a little pot of sugar.
There is a little pot of sugar.
And you...
You dip your finger in it.
And you pull the...
One single grain of sugar
is at the tip of your finger.
Then imagine...
I would like to meditate inside that single grain of sugar.
So shrink your mind.
It gets smaller and smaller.
You open a small door in the grain of sugar.
And you duck inside.
Inside.
It's very surprising, because it's
a very comfortable pretty big meditation room inside the grain of sugar
and you meditate inside the grain of sugar.
.
Super quiet.
You can't hear it.
The heart is beating way outside, but you can hear it.
It's very different.
but you cannot hear it anymore.
Thank you.
Now inside the grain of sugar, start to imagine the whole Pacific Ocean.
So it's kind of amazing.
It's incredible.
inside of a single grain of sugar.
The whole Pacific Ocean.
And in the very middle of the ocean,
a single drop of rain
falls on the quiet ocean.
And a ripple starts to move in a circle.
Slowly, from the middle of the ocean,
towards California, towards Mexico, Baja, towards China,
towards Malaysia,
and follow those ripples
with your mind.
Slowly crossing the entire Pacific Ocean.
And your mind is expanding like the whole ocean.
Inside the grain of sugar.
And in the middle of the ocean,
a ripple starts to move in a circle.
Slowly crossing the entire Pacific Ocean.
And your mind is expanding like the whole ocean.
Now at the sky.
The blue sky is as wide as the ocean.
And inside the grain of sugar.
Your mind becomes as wide and as high as the blue sky.
Thank you.
Now let's go more quiet.
Each step we are going more and more quiet.
Now let's try to turn off our thoughts.
Like we turn a light switch off.
Like when we turn off the lights.
So when I count to three,
try to turn off all your thoughts.
Then we'll stay quiet for a short time.
Then some thought will try to talk again.
Then, de repente va a aparecer algún pensamiento.
Catch it.
Tómalo.
And turn it off like a light switch.
Y apágalo como apaga la luz.
So stay like a guard watching your mind.
Quédate como un guardia viendo tu mente.
If the mind tries to talk.
Si la mente trata de hablar.
Then gently turn it off.
Gentilmente apágalo.
Here we go.
Thank you.
We're also going to turn our mind off, like a light switch, but if the mind tries to
talk, we are not going to fight, let him talk, and don't listen to him.
This is the most quiet state of mind.
We turned off the mind, turn off the thoughts, but if new thoughts come up like clouds in
the sky, just let them go, don't fight with them, because the fighting also makes noise.
Okay?
And let them fade away.
Okay.
There we go.
Nothing faded away.
Thank you.
Now imagine from the sky
above the ocean
comes a beautiful vision
and this is
one of the
teachers in your life
is coming down
through the sky
sitting on a beautiful flower
could be a lotus
could be a rose
but they are very very beautiful
choose
one of the teachers in your life
we are all lucky we have many teachers in our life
we have parents, mom and dad
we have the school teachers
maybe you have sports teachers
or a music teacher
or an art teacher
and then later in our life
we have people who taught us our job
and then we have our wife or husband or children
who were teachers for us
many of us have children
that beautiful religious teachers, in the church or the mosque, synagogue.
And then all of us have historical teachers, like Jesus, Muhammad, Buddha.
So choose one of them, you have many choices, ask the teacher to come on this beautiful
flower, through the sky, and come and sit in front of you, you are both in the sky,
and ask them if they will sit with you.
So ask them for a few minutes to meditate together.
Ask them if they give you their blessing for your mind, and for your meditation.
We're going to sit with the teacher quietly, for a few minutes.
And then we'll sit.
stop for today. So, try to focus these last few minutes. Enjoy having your teacher with
you and enjoy the quiet. Okay, here we go.
Okay, here we go.
Here we go.
And we're gonna take three deep breaths.
And please don't open your eyes yet.
.
Okay.
We made a lot of good karma by meditating, it's direct, raw, good karma, and so let's
share it with other people.
In Guadalajara, in Mexico, the whole country, and in this whole world, three long exhales,
breathe away the good karma, share it with the whole world.
And slowly open your eyes.
I like to take a stretch personally, and I like to stretch.
Please drink a glass of water.
Drink a lot while you're here, okay?
Bring water with you and drink, okay?
We're going to take a break in 15 minutes.
But I thought if you have some questions, they can be about meditation, or they can
be about anything.
And Tim, you guys have a microphone yet?
Okay.
You'll just have to ask loud, okay?
And Seiji and I will repeat the question.
Any questions?
Don't be shy.
Enrique?
Okay.
So my question is, why do women have to endure such pain during labor?
Okay good question.
So they say when a great being is born, like Buddha, they don't cause any pain to their
mother.
And Buddha came out of his mother, his mother was holding on a tree like this.
Her name was Maya.
And he just pop.
He just popped out of her spine and she didn't have any pain at all.
So they say, if we're not very good people yet, when we're born, we hurt our mother.
And that's also a little bit of a bad karma.
And of course you can't hurt anybody unless they already have bad seeds.
And then they say, really good people, they are born like in the middle of a lotus or
something.
Like there's a famous Tibetan saint called the Padmasambhava.
Padmasambhava.
There's a Tibetan saint called Padmasambhava.
And he was born inside of a lotus.
Patanjali, the Yoga Sutra author?
His mother just put some water like that and then he popped down.
Put means fall down into the water, called Anjali.
Patanjali.
That's where it comes from.
His mother put her hands and she had water and it just fell and that means patanjali.
And Jesus was born, we say miraculously.
We say miraculously.
And the Diamond Cutter Sutra says there are four ways to be born.
It's called kené hi, kené hi.
First one is called gong gu, gong gu, gong gu.
It's called gong gu, gong gu.
It's called gong gu.
He said, he said, he says, he has four ways to be born and he has four ways to be born.
He says, he has four ways to be born.
What are those four ways of being born?
Four ways of being born.
Cutter Sutra, says there are four ways to be born. It's called
KHE NAS SHIS, KHE NAS SHIS. First one is called KONG SKYES, born from egg, like
birds. Sometimes they are called DVI BYA, DVI BYA, born twice. Why?
Yeah, first the egg pops out, that's the first time. Then the egg opens, that's the second
time. So that's the second kind of birth. Then birth from womb, which causes a lot of
pain to the mom and to the child, because of the bad seeds in both of them.
And then ZU TE SKYES, ZU TE SKYES means born like a miracle, like Jesus.
And Jesus, and Buddha, no pain to the mother. So these are the four different
ways. Then recently I was, I forgot, oh someone
had a, their father died. And they asked me for some help. And I sent them an essay
my teacher wrote, about when people die. And people asked him questions. And he said,
ZU TE SKYES, ZU TE SKYES, ZU TE SKYES, ZU TE SKYES, ZU TE SKYES, ZU TE SKYES, ZU TE SKYES, ZU TE SKYES.
And then he answered them about how people die.
And in that essay, which was written about 23 years ago, he said, by the way, even though
it's bad seeds that cause the pain to the mother during birth,
to give birth to children is a very, very intense good seed. So to give life to another
being is like almost uncountable good seeds. Cool. Okay. Okay. All right. Thank you.
You choose
Last night, you talk about
Last night, you talk about the vision that someone has after they
see emptiness directly.
Will you repeat that two more times?
They have the vision that they see all the countless beings in the universe.
Tiene una visión en la cual ven a todos los seres en el universo.
Y hablaste de ello, you spoke about it briefly yesterday.
Y hablaste de ello muy brevemente.
Once in another teaching, una vez en otra enseñanza.
Dijiste una, you spoke about it longer, dijiste una charla más extensa.
At the end of that teaching, you said something quite shocking.
Al final de esta enseñanza, dijiste algo que nos sorprendió.
You said, you say, every single face in the universe, dijiste que vemos toda y cada una de las caras en el universo.
And you said, there is a number, dijiste que hay un número.
I was wondering how either of those could relate to emptiness.
Y me estaba preguntando, ¿cómo es que algunos de esos se relacionan con la vacuidad?
Okay, let's talk about it.
Muy bien, hablemos de ello.
So, when you see emptiness directly,
Cuando percibimos la vacuidad directamente,
what's happening physically,
lo que está pasando físicamente,
and you know because you're such a cool yoga teacher,
y lo sabes porque eres un maestro de yoga muy cool,
all your channels, your nadis, open completely.
So you have 72,000 inner channels.
Canales internos.
Three main ones.
Tres principales.
And the little one never opens completely.
El de en medio no se abre completamente.
When you die,
it opens very briefly,
for a few seconds.
And when you have orgasm in sex,
it will open completely just for a few seconds.
It will open completely just for a few seconds.
También se abre completamente por el sexo.
For a few seconds.
So some people say,
Oh, Gesh-la, sex must be a good method to open your channels.
Algunas personas dicen que el sexo es una buena forma de abrir tus canales.
It's okay, but the next moment it closes more tightly than before.
Está bien, pero el siguiente momento se cierra todavía más duro que antes.
That's probably why your husband falls asleep.
Y esa es probablemente la razón por la cual tu esposo se duerme después.
So that method is not too long,
it's not long-lasting.
Ese método no dura mucho.
But then the deeper reason we do yoga
is to open that middle channel
and keep it open.
And then if you open it wide enough,
you will see emptiness.
So there's a famous saying called,
chi nang tab la so war pe
So you can see emptiness using inner method and outer method.
Inner method is meditation.
And study the two husbands in the kitchen.
And then the outer method is manipulate your channels.
Y los métodos externos es manipulando los canales con yoga.
Or it could be swimming or any good exercise.
Un buen ejercicio.
And together the combination is very powerful.
So on the day you see emptiness directly,
Y en el día en que percibes la vacuidad directamente,
Then on the day you see emptiness directly,
And then the day you see emptiness directly,
This central channel opens up completely, and it stays open for about 24 hours.
Pretty open, and so in the first 20 minutes or something, you see emptiness directly.
But after you come out of that meditation, the channel is still open, and it's starting to close slowly.
Not like after sex, okay?
And it will take, until you sleep, it takes about 10, 12 hours to really close.
So during that time, your mind is free.
You can see things which you cannot normally see.
One of the interesting things is you can read other people's minds for the rest of the day.
It's kind of really strange.
And then, of course,
the most beautiful thing is with your eyes closed, but you are not meditating on emptiness anymore,
you start to see faces, one by one.
And it feels like...
Okay, so Stanley took me swimming in the hotel in China.
I thought, oh, this is good with yoga, it's also good.
But I get freckles very easy.
So I'm looking for an indoor swimming pool.
I'm looking for an indoor swimming pool.
Near my house.
And there's only one.
It's in a casino.
And I never...
I went into a casino once in my life.
With my dad.
And also you're not allowed to pay to swim there.
So I asked the hotel manager for a meeting.
And I said, I have a lot of friends in China.
They love to gamble.
And if you let me swim in the pool for free,
I will prepare some advertising for you.
I'm going to prepare some advertising for you.
So they said, okay, you know.
I've been swimming there for about a year.
And they forgot to ask me to do any advertisement.
And I didn't remind them.
But it's kind of very sad place.
It's owned by the native Americans.
So it's their own country, legally it's their own country.
And in their law, you can smoke inside the building.
So the whole casino is covered with smoke.
Except for the swimming pool.
And there are old people playing this machine.
And it's very sad.
Their face also looks like smoke.
So they push this lever.
And then three pictures go like this.
If the three cherries come up, you win money.
And why am I talking about this?
I don't know.
Why am I talking about that?
In your meditation,
faces start to come up like this slot machine.
And you don't know what's going on.
You're just kind of watching.
And your mom's face come up.
Then you think,
there's a very natural reaction.
Because your channel's open.
You say, I love you, mom.
I will take care of you.
Don't worry.
I'll take care of you.
Then the slot machine move again.
And then your father's face come up.
And you're like, you too, dad.
Don't worry.
I'll take care of you also.
Then your brother.
Then all your other family.
And then people you knew in school or your job.
But it's all one by one.
And then people you don't know.
And you're like, I'll take care of you.
Don't worry.
I'll take care of you.
And it starts to speed up.
Then animals start.
So you finish all the people.
Seven billion people.
You finish the seven billion people.
One by one.
And then you start with all the animals.
First your pet dog.
Your cat.
All the mice you caught in the retreat.
I'll take care of you.
Don't worry.
I don't know about your three-year retreat.
But in my three-year retreat,
I spent a lot of time watching the ants.
That's my television. Each ant come up. I'll take care of you also, birds, fish, you finish all of them.
I think the number is a hundred billion or something in this world, animals.
Then starts face from people from next planet.
It speeds up, it speeds up.
Time is also coming from your seeds.
In 20 minutes, you see every living being in the universe.
You say, I will take care of you.
Then I think that's called Arya Bodhisattva.
They had this experience, direct experience, of wanting to take care of everybody.
They saw emptiness.
They saw emptiness before that.
Yes.
Then they saw emptiness, it opened up their channel.
Which is why we do yoga.
Because their channel didn't close yet, it will close by evening.
By the time you go to sleep, it will be pretty much closed.
They can see all these beings directly.
That's the connection between seeing emptiness and real bodhichitta.
Bodhichitta experience of an Arya.
This is the connection between the direct perception of emptiness and real bodhichitta in the mind of an Arya.
Just the extra thing to tell you.
It's hard to have a bad day after that.
It's possible.
It happens.
You do have grumpy days.
Things go wrong.
But in general, it's almost impossible to be unhappy after that.
Because your life has a purpose.
It's very beautiful.
Okay, maybe we take a break.
That's a good place.
I'll do some more questions in the afternoon.
Okay, so let's take a break.
And we'll start the lam rim.
Okay.